Guide to the George Y. Shevelov Papers,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
George Y. Shevelov Papers,
1922-2001.
Shevel'ov, IUrii Volodymyrovych
15 linear ft. (30 document boxes).
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library New York, NY. 10027
BA#0401
4078070
The papers comprise correspondence, writings, memoirs, personal documents, research notes, printed materials, photographs of Iurii Shevel'ov, prominent scholar, Slavic linguist, philologist, literary historian, and literary critic, longtime professor of Slavic philology at Columbia University.
Biographical Note
Iurii Shevel'ov (aka George Y.Shevelov, pseudonyms Iurii Sherekh, Hryhorii Shevchuk, and others), Slavic linguist, philologist, essayist, literary historian, and literary critic; full member of the Shevchenko Scientific Society since 1949 and of the Ukrainian Academy of Arts and Sciences since 1945, was born 17 December 1908 in Kharkiv (some sources, however, indicate Łomża, Poland, then part of the Russian Empire). He studied under Leonid Bulakhovsky at Kharkiv University, graduated and lectured there in Slavic linguistics (1939–1943). He emigrated to Germany during the war and received his Ph.D. degree frоm the Free University of Munich in 1949. He taught there from 1946 to 1949, and then at the University of Lund, Sweden form 1950 to 1952. He was one of the organizers of émigré literary life in Germany and was a vice-president of the literary association "MUR" (1945–1949). After settling in the United States, he served as lecturer in Russian and Ukrainian at Harvard University (1952–1954), associate professor (1954–1958) and professor of Slavic philology at Columbia University from 1958 to his retirement in 1977. He was a founding member of the "Slovo", Association of Ukrainian Writers in Exile. From 1959 to 1961 and from 1981 to 1986 Shevel'ov served as President of the Ukrainian Academy of Arts and Sciences in New York, and editor in-chief of the Ukrainian émigré journal Suchasnist’ (1978–1981). In 1991, Shevel'ov became a foreign member of the National Academy of Sciences of Ukraine.
Iurii Shevel'ov is the author of numerous books and articles on Slavic philology and linguistics and the history of literature and literary criticism. He died 12 April 2002 in New York.
Scope and Content
The bulk of the collection consists of Iurii Shevel'ov's professional and personal correspondence, his manuscripts and research notes. There are also documents, biographical and background materials, photographs, and writings by other authors. The material in the collection is arranged in five series.
Shevel'ov corresponded with many prominent scholars, writers, and literary critics including Peeter Arumaa, Ivan Bahrianyi, Vasyl' Barka, Dmytro Chyzhevs'kyi, Petr Grigorenko, Roman Jakobson, Milan Kundera, Horace Lunt, Mihajlo Mihajlov, George Szell, Boris Unbegaun, Wiktor Weintraub, and many others.
The collection contains Shevel'ov's writings in a variety of genres, such as his early poetry, professional articles, monographs, reviews, and essays (including works of his student years), memoirs, etc. Files include published and unpublished works, extensive drafts and research notes, fragments and uncompleted manuscripts.
Photographs in the collection primarily are Shevel'ov's photos of 1970s-1990s but there are also photos of other people including such prominent figures as Hanna Nakonechna and Vasyl' Simovych, his family and friends.
There are cross-references provided throughout the finding aid. When the cross-reference refers to another item within the same series, the reference includes the specific name or title and box and folder number (this also applies to the references within same subseries and sub-subseries). If the cross-reference is to an item in another series, the reference includes the series number, series name, folder title, and box and folder numbers (this also applies to references to the items in another subseries and sub-subseries).
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in five series:
Series I: Correspondence, 1950-2001
Subseries I.1: Correspondence with Individuals, 1950-2001
Subseries I.2: Correspondence with Organizations, 1951-2001
Series II: Writings, 1926-1990s
Subseries II.1: Memoirs, "Ia - mene - meni", undated
Subseries II.2: Articles and Monographs, 1929-1998
Subseries II.3: Reviews, 1940s-1990s
Subseries II.4: Fragments, undated
Subseries II.5: Poetry, 1926-1969
Subseries II.6: Drafts, Notes, and Research Materials, 1930s-1990s
Series III: Documents, Biographical and Background Materials, 1945-2000
Series IV: Photographs, 1922-1994
Series V: Writings by others, undated, 1970s-2001
Subjects
Alsop, Joseph, 1910-1989.; Andiievs'ka, Emma.; Andrukhovych, IUrii, 1960-; Arumaa, Peeter, 1900-; Bahrianyi, Ivan.; Baley, Virko.; Barka, Vasyl'.; Belotserkovskii, Vadim, 1928-; Bilets'kyi, Leonid, 1882-1955.; Bilinsky, Yaroslav.; Bilokin', Serhii.; Bohachevsky-Chomiak, Martha.; Boichuk, Bohdan.; Boiko, Iurii.; Bondar-Tereshchenko, Ihor.; Borman, Arkadii, 1891-; Carynnyk, Marco.; Chaplenko, Vasyl'.; Cholhan, Ilarion.; Chubatyi, M. (Mykola), 1889-1975.; Demkovych-Dobrians'kyi, Mykhailo.; Drach, Ivan.; Dziuba, Ivan, 1931-; Fedenko, Panas.; Fishbein, Moisei, 1946-; Fizer, John.; Frantsuzhenko, Mykola.; Garde, Paul.; Giedroyc, Jerzy.; Grabowicz, George G.; Grigorenko, P.G., (Petr Grigorevich), 1907-; Halle, Morris.; Hamm, Josip.; Hirniak, Iosyp, 1895-; Hnativ, Mykola.; Hnizdovsky, Jacques, 1915-1985.; Hordyns'kyi, Sviatoslav, 1906-; Hryshko, Vasyl' I., 1914-; Humenna, Dokiia.; Huuttl-Folter, Gerta.; Ianiv, Volodymyr.; Izars'kyi, Oleksa.; Jakobson, Roman, 1896-1982.; Kachurovs'kyi, Ihor.; Karpovich, Michael, 1888-1959.; Keis, Vitalii.; Klynovyi, IUrii, 1909-; Koneski, Blaze.; Korotych, Vitalii Oleksiiovych.; Kosach, Iurii.; Koshelivets', Ivan; Kravtsiv, Bohdan, 1904-; Kubiiovych, Volodymyr, 1900-; Kundera, Milan.; Kuzelia, Zenon, 1882-1952.; Kysilevs'kyi, K. (Kost').; Lawrynenko, Jurij.; Liaturyns'ka, Oksana.; Livyts'ka-Kholodna, Natalia; Luckyj, George Stephen Nestor, 1919-2001.; Lunt, Horace Gray, 1918-; Lyman, Leonid, 1922-; Mazon, Andre, 1881-1967.; Mihajlov, Mihajlo, 1934-2010.; Moroz, Valentyn Iakovych, 1936-; Mosely, Philip E. (Philip Edward), 1905-1972.; Mykhalevych, Mykhailo.; Nakonechna, Hanna.; Nytchenko, Dmytro.; Obolenskii, Dmitrii Dmitrievich, kniaz'.; Odarchenko, Petro, 1903-; Ohloblyn, Oleksander, 1899-; Os'machka, Todos', 1895-1962.; Palii, Lida.; Pavlychko, Dmytro Vasyl'ovych.; Pavlychko, S.D. (Solomiia Dmytrivna).; Pavlyshyn, Marko.; Pevnyi, Bohdan.; Pocheptsov, G. G. (Georgii Georgievich).; Polanski, Kazimierz, 1929-; Poltava, Leonid, 1921-; Pritsak, Omeljan.; Pyziur, Eugene, 1917-; Raeff, Marc.; Rubchak, Bohdan.; Rudnytsky, Ivan L. (Ivan Lysiak), 1919-1984.; Rymaruk, Ihor.; Samchuk, Ulas.; Senn, Alfred.; Sevcenko, Ihor.; Shlemkevych, Mykola, 1894-1966.; Simmons, Ernest J. (Ernest Joseph), 1903-1972.; Simovych, Vasyl', 1880-1944.; Slavutych, IAr, 1918-; Smal-Stocki, Roman, 1893-1969.; Solovii, IUrii.; Stefanovych, Oleksa, 1900-1970.; Struk, Danylo Husar, 1940-1999.; Sverstiuk, IEvhen.; Szell, George, 1897-1970.; Tarnavs'kyi, Iurii.; Tschizewskij, Dmitrij, 1894-1977.; Unbegaun, Boris Ottokar, 1898-1973.; Vasmer, Max, 1886-1962.; Vernadsky, George, 1887-1973.; Vetukhiv, Mykhailo Oleksiievych, 1902-1959.; Vovk, Vira, 1926-; Wynar, Lubomyr Roman, 1932-; Weintraub, Wiktor.; Zabuzhko, O. S. (Oksana Stefanivna).; Zales'ka Onyshkevych, Larysa M. L.; Zhuravlev, V. K. (Vladimir Konstantinovich).; Zuievs'kyi, Oleh, 1920-1996.; Criticism--Ukraine.; Emigration and immigration--Soviet Union--20th century.; Linguistics.; Philologists--Ukraine.; Slavic languages--Grammar.; Slavic languages--History.; Slavic philology.; Ukrainian Americans.; Ukrainian language.; Ukrainian language--History.; Ukrainian literature--History and criticism.; Ukrainian philology.; Correspondence.; Memoirs.; Photographs.
Access Restrictions
This collection has no restrictions.
This collection is located on-site.
Acquisition
1981 Correspondence George Y. Shevelov Gift
1982 Correspondence George Y. Shevelov Gift
- Series I: Correspondence, 1950-2001
  The series consists of Shevel'ov's professional and personal correspondence with various people and organizations and includes letters from many prominent figures. Correspondence may include various related materials, such as manuscripts and clippings. Organized into two subseries.
  - Subseries I.1: Correspondence with Individuals, 1950-2001
    Contains professional and personal letters (some with carbon replies) of various individuals including many prominent scholars, writers, poets, and public figures. Arranged alphabetically. Group, unidentified, and outgoing letters stored at the end of the series. Unidentified correspondence doesn't have formal organization and outgoing correspondence organized in chronological sequence.
    - Adamovich, Anton, New York, 1952-1954 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Akseniv, Andrii, Sunnyvale, CA, 1982-1987 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Allen, John E., undated, New York, 1967-1968 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Allworth, Edward, New York, 1969-1980 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Alsop, Joseph, Washington D.C., 1974 (2 letters) (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Alt, Theresa, Brunswick (ME), Ithaca (NY), Leningrad, Warsaw, Zagreb, 1971-1990 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Andiievs’ka, Emma, Munich, 1978-1984 (6 letters): see also postcards dated 1993 and signed by her in Koshelivets' (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Andriienko, Kostiantyn, Kaniv, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Andrukhovych, Iurii, Ivano-Frankivs’k, undated (1 letter) (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Andrusyshyn, Kost’, Saskatoon, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Antonii, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Antonovych, Marko Dmytrovych, Montreal, undated, 1969-1998 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Antonovych, Omelian and Tetiana, Washington D.C., 1982-1989 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Arkhimovych, Oleksandr, New York, 1966 1969 (see also Ukrains'ka Vil'na Akademiia Nauk) (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Arumaa, Peeter, Bromma, Stockholm, undated, 1951-1956 (12 letters) (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Asher, Oksana, New York, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Aslanov, S.G., Paris, 1967-1978 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Astman, Marina, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Austerllitz, Robert, New York, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Auty, Robert, Oxford, 1975-1977 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Avril, F., Paris, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Bacic, Jakov, New York, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Bahrianyi, Ivan, 1951 (1 letter) (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Baker, Robert, Bloomington, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Bakula, Boguslaw, Poznan, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Balei, Petro, Canyon Country (CA), 1977-1981 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Baley, Virko, Las Vegas, 1978 (2 letters) (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Baran, Stefan, Munich-Freimann, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Baranczak, Stanislaw, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Barka, Vasyl’: (Box 1, Folder 20 to 23)
      - To Ol’ha Petrivna Malanchuk, Glen Spey (NY), 1979 (photocopy of postcard) (Box 1, Folder 20)
      - To Iurii Shevel'ov, Glen Spey (NY), no places; undated, 1962-1997 (35 letters and postcards) (Box 1, Folder 20 to 23)
    - Barnstead, John A., Brighton (MA), 1973 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Beeson, Nora: see Subseries I.2: Correspondence with Organizations--American Slavic and East European Review (Box 16, Folder 6)
    - Belcher, Etrenne, Vienna, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Belknap, Robert L., New York, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Belotserkovskii, Vadim, Munich, no places, 1979-1980 (10 letters) (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Bernards, Voldemar, Springfield (MA), 1957 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Bethin, Christina Y., Stony Brook, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Bida, Konstiantyn, Ottawa, 1956-1979 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Bidwell, Charles E., Pittsburgh, 1966-1968 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Bidwell, Natasha, Pittsburgh, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Bilets’kyi, Leonid, Winnipeg, 1954 (5 letters) (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Bilins'ky, Yaroslav, Newark (DE), 1969-1985 (21 letters) (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Bilokin’, Serhii, Kyiv, Washington D.C., undated, 1992-1998 (6 letters, printed article by S.Bilokin’ “Pro natsional’nu arystokratiiu Ukrainy”) (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Bilous, A., New York, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Bird, Thomas E., New York, 1973 1983 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Birnbaum, Henrik, Farsta, Stockholm (Sweden), Los Angeles, 1958-1992 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Bjornflaten, Jan Ivar, Oslo, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Bluhme, H., Munich, 1968 1972 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Boba, Imre, Seattle, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Bohachevsky-Chomiak, Martha, Purchase (NY), McLean (VA), Washington D.C., 1979-1991 (8 letters) (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Bohdan, Ihor, Warsaw, 1989 1991 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Bohuslavets’, Lesia, undated (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Boichuk, Bohdan, New York, 1966-1985 (8 letters) (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - Boiko, Iurii (aka Jurij Bojko-Blochyn), Munich, no place; undated, 1951-1997 (47 letters and postcards, 2 notes: one on the page with a typed poem and another one on the postcard written by L.Boiko) (Box 1, Folder 36 to 38)
    - Boiko, L., Munich, 1968-1980 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - Boiko, M., Bloomington, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - Bolyns’kyi, Bohdan, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - Bonamour, J., Paris, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - Bondar-Tereshchenko, Ihor, Kharkiv, 1994-1995 (9 letters and postcards; 1 printed article) (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - Borets’kyi, Mykhailo, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - Borman, Arkadii, New York, 1953 (2 letters, 1 carbon reply) (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - Borshchak, (?), Washington, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - Botsford, Carolina R., New York, undated, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - Botsiurkiv, Bohdan, Edmonton, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - Botvinnik, (?), Moscow, 1973-1974 (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - Brauer, Herbert, Marburg, 1962-1986 (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - Briukhovets’ka, Larysa, Kyiv, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - Briukhovets’kyi, Viacheslav, Kyiv, undated, 1990-2000 (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - Bromlei, S.: see his letter of 1976 to Oldrich Leska in Leska's correspondence
    - Browne, Wayles: see Alt, Theresa
    - Brugsch, H.G., Boston, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 45)
    - Brukhis, Mikhail (aka Bruchis, M.), Urbana-Champaign, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 45)
    - Buiniak, Viktor O. (aka O.Buiniak), Saskatoon, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 46)
    - Bures, Daniel, Middlebury, undated (Box 1, Folder 46)
    - Burevii, Oksana, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 46)
    - Burghardt, Vol’fram, London, Sarcelles (France), 1961-1979 (Box 1, Folder 47)
    - Buriachok, A., 1993 see Horbach (Horbach's letter to Shevel'ov written on a back of Buriachok's letter to Horbach)
    - Buriakivets’, IUrii, New York, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 48)
    - Burkin, I., Syracuse, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 48)
    - Burmystrovych, Iurii Iakovlevych, Abakan, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 48)
    - Burnham, James, Kent (CT), 1953 (Box 1, Folder 48)
    - Burstynsky, Edward, Toronto, 1975-1979 (Box 1, Folder 48)
    - Burtniak, M., Hamilton (Ontario), Miami, 1957 1960 (Box 1, Folder 48)
    - Byrnes, Robert F., Bloomington (IN), 1962 (Box 1, Folder 48)
    - Carlton, T.R., Edmonton, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Carynnyk, Marco, Toronto, 1978 1980 (2 letters) (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Catalan, Diego, Berkeley, undated, 1955-1956 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Chaikovs’kyi, Ievhen, Philadelphia, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Chaplenko, Vasyl’, 1978 (1 letter) (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Chemerys, Ivan, Boras, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Chew, Jack, Buffalo, Toronto, Japan, undated, 1953-1972 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Cholhan, Ilarion, 1988-2000 (8 letters and postcards) (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Chopyk, Dan Bohdan (aka Bohdan Chopyk), Boulder, Salt Lake City, 1966 1971 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Chornii, I., Munich, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Chub, Dmytro: see Nytchenko, Dmytro
    - Chubatyi, Mykola, Mahwan (NJ), 1953-1954 (5 letters; with replies) (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Chumachenko, Viktor, Krasnodar, undated, 1993-2000 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Chumak, Valentyn, Kyiv, 1991-1993 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Chvany, Ann, Harvard, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Chykalenko, Oksana, various places, undated, 1951-1975 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Chyzhevs'ka, Tatiana, 1978-1979 (with related items) (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Chyzhevs'kyi, Dmytro, various places, undated, 1954-1975 (microfilmed, MN#2000-2014-1) (Box 2, Folder 11 to 14)
      - To Iurii Shevel'ov (73 letters and postcards; some with replies) (Box 2, Folder 11 to 14)
      - To Ivan Zamsha, 1972 (photocopy of one letter) (Box 2, Folder 14)
      - To unidentified, 1972 (photocopy of one letter) (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Cocron, Fritz, Vienna, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Cohen, Gerald, Missouri, 1969-1988 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Czyzewski, Feliks, Lublin, 1990-1997 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Dal'nyi, Mar'ian Hryhorovych (aka Horhota), Guelph, Canada, 1980-1997 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Danko, Osyp, New Haven, 1974-1980 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Danylenko, Andrii Ivanovych, Kharkiv, 1993-1999 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Davyskyba, Mykola, Mattapan (MA), 1952-1954 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - DeArmong, Richard C., Seattle, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Decaux, E., 1960 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Demkovych-Dobrians'kyi, Mykhailo (aka Dobrians'kyi, Mykhailo), London, 1952-1985 (17 letters and postcards) (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Denysiuk, Mykola, Buenos-Aires, 1952-1957 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Derbyshire, William W., Binghamton (NY), 1967 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Dezso, Laslo: his letter to Oldrich Leska filed with Leska's correspondence (Box 7, Folder 20)
    - Diachenko, Valerii, Kharkiv, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Dickenmann, Fraunfeld, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Diels, Paul, Munich, 1950-1955 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Dima, undated, 1953-1954 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Domazar, Serhii, Australia, 1958-1979 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Dorfman, Eugene, New York, 1954-1955 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Doroshenko, Volodymyr, 1956-1957 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Dotsenko, Rostyslav, Kyiv, 1992-1998 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Dovbenko, Katia, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Dovhal', S., Munich, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Drach, Ivan, Kyiv, 1967 (2 letters) (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Dravin(?), K., Lund, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Dravins, Velte, Stockholm, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Dubko-Fylypchak, Iryna, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Dudko, Viktor, Kyiv, 1992 1997 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Durovic, Lubomir, Lund, 1980-1985 (Slaviska Institutionen vid Lunds Universitet) (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Dvorko, Henrikh, Kyiv, 1994 (with typescript of his article "Ukraina-IEvropa-Amerykans'kyi diad'ko") (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Dychkivna, Evdokiia, undated (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Dzendzelivs'kyi, Iosyp Oleksiiovych, Uzhhorod, 1991-1996 (see also his letter to Oldrich Leska in: Leska correspondence) (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Dzhaparidze, D.A., Milton-on-Hudson (NY), 1959 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Dziuba, Ivan, Kyiv, 1989-2000 (26 letters and postcards) (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Edgerton, William B., Indiana, 1964 1966 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Eekman, Thomas, Los Angeles, 1969-1971 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Enesku, Natalia, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Erlich, Viktor, New Haven, 1966 1978 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Fedenko, Panas, Munich, 1977 (1 letter) (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Fedevych, Roman, Melbourne, 1974 1976 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Fedorenko, Valentyna, Costa Mesa (CA), undated, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Fedyshyn, Oleh, undated, 1977-1978 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Ferrell, James, Ann Arbor, undated, 1953-1979 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Fesenko, Andrii (aka Andrew D. Fessenko), Washington, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Fink, W., Munich, 1964-1966 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Fishbein, Moisei, Jerusalem, Munich, 1979-1995 (11 letters, typed poems) (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Fishman, Joshua A., New York, 1977 1990 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Fizer, John (aka Ivan Fizer), New Brunswick (NJ), 1967-1994 (17 letters. See also: Subseries I.2:Correspondence with Organizations--"Slovo", Box 16, Folder 13) (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Flier, Michael S., Los Angeles, Cambridge (MA), 1969-1995 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Fontana, Elisabete, Rome, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Fortune, Richard, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Foster, C.R., Jr., Wilmington, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Frantsuzhenko, Mykola (aka Mykola Virnyi), 1991 (1 letter) (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Freidhof, Gerd, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Fried, Robin, New Haven, undated (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Friedman, Victor A., 1977-1981 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Garde, Paul, various places, 1969-1979 (24 letters and postcards) (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Gerhardt, Dietrich, Hamburg, Munster, 1951-1959 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Gerych, Iu., Ottawa, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Ghoshal, Satyajyoti, Calcutta, 1970-1971 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Giedroyc, Jerzy, Maisons-Laffitte, 1950s-1980 (26 letters) (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Ginzburg, Mikhail Saulovich, Bloomington, 1957 1958 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Grabowicz, George G., Cambridge (MA), undated, 1972-1984 (7 letters and postcards) (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Gregg, Richard, Amherst, New York City, undated, 1958 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Gregoret, Maia, St.Paul (MN), 2000 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Gribble, Charles E., Columbus (OH), 1978-1989 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Grigorenko, Petr Grigor'evich, 1980 (1 letter) (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Grinvaldt, Borys, Los Angeles, undated (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Gritskan, Irina, undated, 1960-1967 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Gudzovs'kyi, A., New York, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Gustafson, Richard F., 1998 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Hablevych, Mariia, L'viv, undated, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Hai-Holovko, O., Winnipeg, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Haievs'kyi, S.: see Syl'vester, Archbishop
    - Haievs'kyi, Valentyn, Los Angeles, 1954-1955 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Hal'chenko, Serhii, Washington, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Haliv, Mykola, 1969-2001 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Halle, Morris, Cambridge (MA), 1955 (1 letter, with reply) (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Hamm, Josip, various places, undated, 1958-1979 (33 letters and postcards) (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Harkins, William E., New York, 1968-1994 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Haro, G., Ohrid, Plovdiv, 1982-1983 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Harris, Jane, Helsinki, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Havrylenko, Oles', Kharkiv, 1993-1994 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - Hejl, Vilem, Munich, Vienna, 1979-1980 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - Henley, Norman, Baltimore, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - Herlihy, Patricia, Cambridge (MA), 1978 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - Hess, Mieczyslaw, Krakow, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - Himka, John-Paul, Edmonton, Krakow, 1975-1980 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - Hirnaik, Iosyp, New York, 1953 1956 (2 letters) (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - Hlobenko, Mykola, Sarcelles, 1950-1955 (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - Hlushchenko, Volodymyr, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - Hnativ, Mykola, Winnipeg, 1980 (1 letter to Suchasnist' (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - Hnizdovsky, Jacques, 1954-1985 (Box 3, Folder 28)
      - To Iurii Shevel'ov (11 letters and postcards, 1 note)
      - To Sviatoslav Hordyns'kyi, 1985 (1 letter along with a photocopy of Sviatoslav Hordyns'kyi's letter to him)
    - Holling, Fred and Harriet, Clackamas, Zagreb, undated, 1958-1969 (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - Holod, Mariia, 1990-1992 (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - Holod, Renata, undated (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - Holubenko, Petro, 1978 1980 (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - Honchariv, Iakiv, Portland, 1954-1982 (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - Horbach, Oleksa & Halia, various places, 1950-1997 (Box 3, Folder 31 to 33)
    - Hordiiev, Ihor, New South Wales, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 34)
    - Hordyns'kyi, Sviatoslav, various places, undated, 1950-1979 (7 letters and postcard, 1 note. See also photocopy of his letter to Jacques Hnizdovs'kyi in Hnizdovs'kyi file, Folder 28) (Box 3, Folder 35)
    - Horhota, Mar'ian Hryhorovych: see Dal'nyi, Mar'ian